The title of our lecture, proximity to nature - has a way to better health?
with question marks.
It might also have the sub -heading, we are on the right track.
Not least with the image you can see here.
My name is Åsa Engström and I am, as I said, professor of nursing,
Also subject representatives there.
Also a nurse and worked primarily in intensive care
And courses linked to it.
And this with the importance of nature is something that is warm to me.
You may introduce yourself.
Päivi Juuso is my name, assistant professor at the department of
Nursing and medical technology.
And just as Åsa says,
Colleague and we have worked and work in many different projects together.
I am a district nurse, primarily worked in sparsely populated areas.
So this with nature is very close really, my everyday life -
And my everyday life.
It will be great fun -
To give this lecture for you.
And also welcomes all of you -
on site and all of you on the web.
Is it really possible to implement?
That is what we will discuss the next moment.
[Päivi:] Yes, exactly.
Then we get into this with, the animals really have -
a positive impact on human health.
How did you understand it, Åsa?
[Åsa:] Yes, we are pretty much agreed that the animals have a very -
Positive impact on our health.
It can create one, what should we say, health and well -being -
So everyday.
To have a spinning cat -
Or a dog near him, maybe we stress down, that we relax.
There are also very good effects when it comes to clean, -
What should we say, in terms of treatment.
This with that, -
a dog or cat or a pet.
Can be both comfort when we are -
lonely and sad.
A company.
It trains us to have social interactions with others.
And in many ways there are both evidence and example -
On the fact that, this is useful for our health.
So what accessibility do we have to nature.
Historically, for example, we know that even Hippocrates -
Built hospitals on open spaces and by lakes.
Just to have access to nature.
And man as a patient -
could roam in nature and thus also find a balance.
In them here, then you talked a lot about these fluids in the body.
So you find a balance between what is sick and what is not sick.
So you find health there.
So there are a lot of people -
Such descriptions.
Also our guru, Florence Nightingale.
Because it is precisely the open spaces that can be health promotion.
There is also always a distinction between that, how close and how much -
Noise is around.
But that there is still an asset -
At least to them here.
Where we really also talk about the opportunity to recover -
By, you usually talk about getting a feeling of -
a context.
But also an opportunity to hear others, -
But still not have to interact.
Depending on how we feel.
So there is this one, you usually talk about, almost like you can pull away.
But still is not completely alone.
This is based on the theories that exist around this meaning -
of nature and the impact of nature on our health.
Do you have something where you want to add?
[Åsa:] No, I think it's -
That you feel safe, in the environment where you are.
Just.
And then we come back a little to them here,
What are the mechanisms behind the impact of this nature.
Here we have written well -being, but health and well -being.
Then we can back back and look a little, the natural environment and its condition.
So size of it, where it is, what it looks like.
It affects what nature contact we have.
Of course, it has significance, -
How far do I have to go to get into this nature.
This, in turn, affects how much time we stay in nature.
It turns out that nature contact also increases our immune system.
So there are many positive aspects in this, except for vitamin D.
And it has to do with our nervous system.
We have this stress cover with cortisol and so on.
Or is it that we can dampen it.
By staying in nature, in fact also so long -
That we really take a deep breath and breathe in.
And then sounds ours ... it gets like unconscious actions really.
It is not something we can always influence, we can learn to handle it.
Then she told me that, yes it may sound a bit strange, -
But I had a friend.
And it was a pine outside my window.
Well, I thought this was interesting.
She told me that -
This number, it said what the weather and wind was.
If it had snowed and so on.
In the evening I said good night to it and in the morning when I woke up, -
So it stood there waiting for me.
Some night they had pulled down the blinds and the blinds -
And she almost panicked when she couldn't look out the window.
She also described it just like this that, yes probably the staff was kind -
And they came in and so on.
But I was very lonely and then I had my pine.
And somehow she described it as, it was me and the numbers to the world.
I was in continued contact with the woman and still keep in touch.
Then we decided to write an article, I asked if it was okay -
Have had contact, about this number.
And there are a lot of theories about this with that -
Animals, which I have been on.
And even nature, can be important.
And that it can be, the other need not be a human being.
Because it was so important and the one that made me move on.
After a while I got a message and then she had sent -
this picture.
I have been allowed to show it.
When she is and visits her pine, outside the hospital in Piteå.
She hugs it.
So she has said, you must never cut down that.
It was her power through this time.
Think it is important.
And I have some of that article if you want -
Bring with you.
It's a short article, there are some there and there are -
Something for a copy if you would like to read.
And as was sick eventually.
Because it was simply too much.
She also described this meaning of being in nature -
And what it did to her.
This description it is, -
Could be almost in any context.
This with stress -related ill health.
As we are in in many and many -
And what it can do.
I read it.
[Reads the quote on the screen]
[Päivi:] mm, exactly.
And here we get into the climate, suddenly.
I think, I can refer back to this previous one.
[Päivi:] And what do we say about the climate and its importance.
[Åsa:] Yes, but we say that the climate is important for health.
What we know here and now, we know that we have a higher average temperature -
than we've ever had.
We know that it brings, -
Storms in different ways.
Floods and such.
This means risks that water will be contaminated.
This means that, for example, we get ticks up here.
These are diseases that may become relevant in a different way.
It affects us in a variety of ways.
And what one can say is that -
There is also a reasoning about, and even a letter -
About this with, how to build sustainable cities.
It is very relevant in Norrbotten.
How to have a sustainable urban environment planning.
To be able to maintain and perhaps reduce transport -
which is also daily transport.
So it has one, what we do definitely has a meaning.
We are also those who may actually do something.
For that, we must remember, those that are the weakest in society -
So, we would eat better, maybe reduce meat.
Should we move more to a greater extent, it is good for us, -
But also good for the environment.
Thus, physically.
[Päivi:] The active choices.
And of course we can't either -
Knit under chair with, maybe our living habits, -
If they looked different.
Had we not been in that situation -
We have been now, these two and a half last years.
And this is probably not something, where it stops.
So it's hard to say, whose is the fault and where does it come from.
But I think, instead of accusing.
I think we have to take -
to make active choices.
It does not mean that you completely end up with everything.
Without, you have to think a little.
Here we can also lift, -
That there is also research in, how can you make care more sustainable -
Because it was actually even when I read to the nurse.
But now you have pinpoint it and show the importance of, -
To make these active choices even in these organizations.
How can we maintain a high patient safety, but still not then, -
Actually wasting, on resources.
[Åsa:] Good.
I think we move on.
[Päivi:] Yes.
[Åsa:] Yes, then we have another question here, which we talked about in the introduction.
This with, can really care, care and rehabilitation -
be implemented outdoors?
[Päivi:] mm.
If we now think that there is evidence that nature and animals -
has a significance for our health and well -being.
Is it also that, we asked ourselves the question, but why is implemented then -
All care, care and rehabilitation mainly indoors.
We did this together, you see down here, we are four editors in a book.
Which is written, thanks to very great help from others.
And where we aim to describe and fill in -
These knowledge gaps available.
Related to these aspects.
Can we conduct care, care, rehabilitation outdoors.
And its health promotion effects, to patients.
Or persons -
that cannot go out.
We have been to it before.
If you think practical examples, can be for example, -
That we are usually rehabilitated back after a stroke.
Then we go indoors on flat floors.
While you can ask for -
Those parts could be done outdoors anyway.
That one had had, care, care and rehabilitation context, -
Thus, the care business near nature, constructed.
We can also see it sometimes in hospitals that it is built.
With the help of all them here.
Now I don't even remember -
How many they are.
Many authors.
[Åsa:] To the right we see, June, only to be called June and Stand -
for the health care of the future.
Maybe then outdoors.
If you are wondering what she has for the title of that, then it is coordinator.
I think that is also something for the future.
To get ours together, -
Both professions and so on.
So yes.
[Päivi:] mm, exactly.
You had an example here, it has been just recently.
I don't know if you have others, but Åsa may tell you a little.
You do not have as a patient, user or accommodation, -
in care, care and rehabilitation in general.
That's really what the article is about.
To notice -
To have these opportunities, actually.
What they propose as a recommendation.
Is that principals and decision makers in healthcare and care.
Takes care of the knowledge that exists, about health -promoting outdoor environments -
potential in care context.
That we have a holistic perspective, which is taken into account in the construction of -
How can these small, medium -sized companies that have businesses -
in the natural resource industry.
As too, some of them are -
Trained healthcare professionals, others not, as it looks here.
But like the rehabilitation garden in Alnarp.
These could promote health among customers, clients.
In our projects, customers, clients have come from various public actors.
During projects, of course, on a voluntary basis.
But we also have this.
Really had follow -up research.
We have a doctoral student, -
who consolidates the area and studying, what do we get for -
Contribution to the research base on this.
What is it like to be a person who gets to test them here, in the northern environment.
If you think, we still have a large part of the year winter.
Until the end of the year, where you can go in.
It goes under the long name,
New Nordic Nature Based Service Models.
It's a very long name, so we got to find a short name.
So we don't slip with the tongue every time at talking about this.
But here I can also say that it is Vasa University.
It is Lapland's vocational college and Oulu vocational college, -
Who has been with us in this.
Except we from LTU.
[Åsa:] I don't know who -
Before starting work training.
For I have seen here that there is the opportunity -
that it can be good. "
It is also part of this context that one is strengthened in one's self -confidence, -
But also his self -esteem.
To be in nature and take in with different senses, to still the senses -
in everyday life.
Is a great help in dealing with life and one's stress.
Then we have to remember that, under these pilots.
Have you not been -
alone with the animals.
All the farms have had animals, -
Where we had a pilot ... no not really everyone.
There has been some garden -
It is really the one, the environmental theory of supportive environments, -
Can you say it is in Swedish.
If you think of the box at the bottom.
There is really when the person feels the worst.
I think that is very interesting really based on this theory.
Because here you show that, you are quite inward.
You can't cope with contact with others.
I have met people who have -
Been sick for stress -related ill health, who says that, no but we ...
... they could nothing, they couldn't even be with animals.
Without it just being in yourself.
That it starts there.
So I think I don't stay here.
Yes, it is interesting this.
We will see then if any questions are related to that part.
[Åsa:] Should I browse?
[Päivi:] Yes, I think so.
Because I see that time goes by.
We also want to flag a little because there is -
Publications in selection, in this project.
And that it comes -
A final report, natural values as a source of well -being.
It will be in Swedish and Finnish.
So it will come soon, during the month of April.
Then it is like a PDF, to download or print.
How to do.